From its humble beginnings in the early
20th century, IIT (ISM) Dhanbad has
forged an extraordinary legacy,
transforming vision into impactful
reality.
Established in 1926, this esteemed
institution has stood tall for nearly a
century, steadily evolving through the
millennium.
What began as the Indian School of Mines
has blossomed into a full-fledged Indian
Institute of Technology, operating with
18 vibrant branches across Engineering,
Applied Sciences, Management Studies,
and Humanities, cementing its place as a
prominent global institution.
This transformation marks a new era,
building upon a centenary of
outperforming achievements in both
academia and industry.
Our campus is a hub of comprehensive
learning, offering a diverse array of
undergraduate, postgraduate, and PhD
programs.
We foster a rich environment for
research, leading to groundbreaking
contributions.
From pioneering the nation's first
Geoarchaeology course to a unique
integrated BTech-MBA program with IIM
Mumbai, our academic offerings reflect a
commitment to forward-thinking
education.
Faculty members are not just educators
but innovators, with individuals like
Prof Sekhar Dutta becoming Fellows of
the Institution of Civil Engineers, UK,
and Prof Anshumali shaping climate
change policy.
Our researchers, like the team that
conducted the first-ever
multiple-layered blasting using smart
design, are at the forefront of
industrial innovation.
IIT (ISM) Dhanbad shines on the global
stage, proudly securing the 20th
position worldwide in
Engineering-Mineral and Mining in QS
rankings, a significant leap and a
testament to our specialized excellence.
Our reach extends beyond the campus
gates through vital community work,
including skill development programs for
local youth and leadership training for
Panchayati Raj Functionaries.
We embrace inclusivity, as demonstrated
by the Uttar Pradesh government's
support for Atul Kumar's IIT education
following Supreme Court intervention,
and our commitment to student well-being
through initiatives like a fully
operational campus creche.
Our alumni, such as Ms Gargi Mishra,
recognized among the top 100 inspiring
women in mining globally, continue to
make us proud.
Even moments of campus joy, like the
viral Diwali rocket video, add to the
vibrant tapestry of student life.
As we continue to drive India's critical
mineral mission and innovate in fields
from Arctic MedTech to Hydrogen Valley
development, IIT (ISM) Dhanbad remains
dedicated to shaping future leaders and
contributing to a brighter tomorrow.